<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Chapter 2 Scroll</string>
    <string name="article_title">Hurricane Alex (2016)</string>
    <string name="article_subtitle">Meteorological history</string>
    <string name="article_text">
        ( source : https://wikipedia.com ) In early January 2016, a stationary front spanned across the <b>western Caribbean</b>, spawning a non-tropical low along its boundary over northwestern Cuba by January 6.[9][10] The low moved northeast ahead of the subtropical jet stream the following day, when its interaction with a shortwave trough produced a cyclonic disturbance at the lower atmospheric levels northeast of the Bahamas.[9][11] This system proceeded northeast toward Bermuda, where unfavorable atmospheric conditions such as strong wind shear, low sea surface temperatures, and dry air initially inhibited tropical or subtropical cyclone formation.[12][11] The system featured a large field of gale-force winds, with maximum sustained winds of 60–65 mph (95–100 km/h).[12] On January 8, it passed about 75 mi (120 km) north of Bermuda, bringing strong winds and heavy rain to the islands. The next day, an unseasonable air pattern blocked the disturbance from continuing along its northeasterly path. Instead, the system turned east-southeast into a region slightly more favorable for subtropical development.[9][14] On January 10, surface pressures below the system\'s core deepened to 979 mbar (hPa; 28.91 inHg) as the surrounding winds reached hurricane-force.[9] Concurrently, a warm-core seclusion at the upper-levels marked the transition to a more symmetric structure,[15] although convective activity near the center remained sparse.[16] Once separated from the jet stream, the cyclone turned sharply to the south-southeast in response to a mid-latitude trough over the central Atlantic, entering a region with warmer waters of 2.7F (1.5C) above average for January.
The system underwent substantial changes to its cyclonic structure on January 11–12: frontal boundaries separated from the core of the cyclone,[9] its core became symmetric,[15] it became co-located with an upper-level low,[nb 1] and intense albeit shallow convection developed atop the circulation. All these factors indicated the storm's transition into a subtropical cyclone by 18:00 UTC on January 12, at which point it was situated 1,150 mi (1,850 km) west-southwest of the Canary Islands and received the name Alex from the National Hurricane Center.[9] The cyclone proceeded to the east-northeast and eventually north-northeast over the next day, steered by the same trough that had enabled the previous southward turn.
    </string>
</resources>